Guide to the Marian Swerdlow Collection on Transport Workers Union of America (TWU), Local 100 WAG.367
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Marian Swerdlow Collection on Transport Workers Union of America (TWU), Local 100
1978-2008
1980-1986
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Swerdlow, Marian, 1949-
WAG.367
3.75 linear feet in 7 manuscript boxes and 1 half manuscript box
Marian Swerdlow (1949 - ) is a sociologist, a former New York City subway conductor, and a former member of the Transport Workers of America (TWU), Local 100. Swerdlow was an active supporter of Local 100 opposition campaigns led by Arnold Cherry in the late 1970s and 1980s, and started the newsletter Hell on Wheels to disseminate information and support the slate of opposition candidates that later became the reform caucus New Directions. The Marian Swerdlow Collection on Transport Workers Union of America (TWU), Local 100 (dated 1978-2008) consists of materials collected by Swerdlow documenting her experiences as a subway conductor, as well as the opposition groups and reform movements within TWU Local 100 in the late 20th century. Materials include newsletters, newspaper clippings, notebooks from meetings, and ephemera concerning actions, strikes, contract campaigns, challenges to incumbent union leadership, Local 100 elections, Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA) engagement with transit workers, and the safety and working conditions of transit workers. Opposition newsletters include Hell on Wheels and Rank and File Advocate. The collection also includes sociological papers and conference presentations by Swerdlow on various labor topics based in part on her personal experiences. This collection documents the working conditions of transit workers, coverage of TWU in the media, and the conflict in leadership within Local 100 between the incumbent Willie James and the reform movement of New Directions.
Scope and Contents
The Marian Swerdlow Collection on Transport Workers Union of America (TWU), Local 100 (dated 1978-2008) consists of materials collected by Swerdlow documenting her experiences as a subway conductor, as well as the opposition groups and reform movements within TWU Local 100 in the late 20th century. Materials include newsletters, newspaper clippings, notebooks from meetings, and ephemera concerning actions, strikes, contract campaigns, challenges to incumbent union leadership, Local 100 elections, Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA) engagement with transit workers, and the safety and working conditions of transit workers. Opposition newsletters include Hell on Wheels and Rank and File Advocate. The collection also includes sociological papers and conference presentations by Swerdlow on various labor topics based in part on her personal experiences. This collection documents the working conditions of transit workers, coverage of TWU in the media, and the conflict in leadership within Local 100 between the incumbent Willie James and the reform movement of New Directions.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the roughly chronological order in which they were received from the donor, with the exception of notebooks which are at the end of the collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Marian Swerdlow in July 2021; the accession number associated with this gift is 2021.032.
Biographical Note
Marian Swerdlow (1949 - ) is a sociologist, a former New York City subway conductor, and a former member of the Transport Workers of America (TWU), Local 100. Swerdlow was an active supporter of Local 100 opposition campaigns led by Arnold Cherry in the late 1970s and 1980s, and started the newsletter Hell on Wheels to disseminate information and support the slate of opposition candidates that later became the reform caucus New Directions. She published a memoir of her experiences, Underground Woman: My Four Years as a New York City Subway Conductor in 1998.
Contracts; Transport workers -- New York (N.Y.); Transport workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State); Labor unions -- Organizing -- New York (N.Y.); Employment & social affairs -- Health and safety at work.; Labor unions -- United States -- Periodicals.; Swerdlow, Marian, 1949-; Transport Workers Union of America. Local 100; New York (State). Metropolitan Transportation Authority; Communist Party of the United States of America
- Transit Exam, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- TWU and Barbaro, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- TWU 100 Opposition -- Meeting Notes, Election Literature, Shop Papers "Soap Box" and "UMCT Vote", 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- TA Conditions -- Newsclippings, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Hell on Wheels -- Drafts, Layouts, First Issue, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- CPUSA Distributions to TWU Members at 207th Street Barn, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- CPUSA Analysis of 1980 Strike (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Grumman Buses Problems -- Newspaper Clippings, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- CPUSA Distribution of Daily World at 126 St. Bus Depot, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Daily World on Transit, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- CPUSA on 1980 Strike (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 1980 Strike -- Village Voice (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Binding Arbitration of Contract -- Unions Gives Up "No Contract, No Work" Policy, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- CPUSA Transit Club Support Work, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Arbitrations on COLA Productivity, Bus Schedules, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Transit -- Westway, Fare Increase, Rider Conditions, Bus Drivres, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Convention Position Paper, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- July 3, 1982 Subway Crash -- Newsclippings, NTSB Report (Box 1, Folder 18)
- TWU Proposed Maternity Leave Rights, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Applications for TA Exam and Conductors' Position, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Campaign Against Fare Increase, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- TWU Health Benefit Trust, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Published by Local 100 and Individual Officers, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Occupational Safety, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Safety, Injuries, Workers Compensation, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Directives to Conductors, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- MTA Mismanagement and Corruption, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Rider Attacks, Workplace Injuries, Rider Injuries, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Humor, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- BAT and Drug Screening, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Grievance Procedures, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Pick Slip, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Other Rank and File Newsletters, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Receipt for Farebox, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 15)
- "The Sheets", 1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Dues Check Off; Loss and Restoration, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- MTA Funding, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- TA EEO Policy, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- CPUSA in Local 100, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- 1982 Contract (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Turks, Willy Murder, 1982-06-22 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Conductor Training Notes, 1982-08 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Conductors Union Meeting Notes, 1982-12-08 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Working Conditions, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- TA Rules for Conductors, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Local 100 Elections, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Workers Compensation, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Rank and File Campaign Against Fare Hike, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Launching Hell on Wheels, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Summer 1983 Slowdown (Box 3, Folder 13)
- "No Lunch" Rank and File Campaign, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- UMCT Opposition Group, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Conductors Union Meeting Notes, 1983-01-12 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Conductors Union Meeting Notes, 1983-02-09 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Conductors Union Meeting Notes, 1983-03-09 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Special Union Meeting Notes, 1983-03-22 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Campaign to End Tier 3, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Conductors Union Meeting Notes, 1983-04-13 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Conductors Union Meeting Notes, 1983-06-08 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Metro North, NJ Transport Strikes, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Committee for a Fighting TWU Spartacist League Front Group, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Track and Power Officers, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Transit Workers for Jackson, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Disciplinary Reports, Appeals, and Letters of Commendation, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Members' Letters Protesting Removal of M. Swerdlow's Steward Credentials, 1984-01 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Safety Campaign, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Fare -- Newsclippings, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Kiley-Gunn Administration, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Binding Arbitration Referendum, 1984-07 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Crew Room Conditions, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- "8 for 8" Grievances and Campaign to Get Pay for Working During Lunch Time, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Working and Riding Conditions -- Newspaper Clippings, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Hell on Wheels Newsletter, Leaflets, 1984-1987 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Straphangers Campaign, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Employee of the Month/Disciplinary Notice, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- MABSTOA Work to Rule, 1985-02 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Rank and File Contract Campaign, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Hell on Wheels, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Notice of Special Union Meeting, 1985-10-30 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Contract Referendum Vote, 1985-08 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Local 100 Elections, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Election Campaign for Delegate, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Courtesy Class, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- No Work Available and Job-Related Illness, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Voice Newsletter, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Seniority Mass Grievance, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- News Articles, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Rank and File Campaign to Support P9 Strikers, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Grimes (Railroad Clerk), 1986 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Campaign Against Involuntary Carwash Overtime, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Short Pay Grievance, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Health and Safety, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Shop Stewards Class, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Hell on Wheels -- Newsletters, Meeting Notes, Correspondence, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Steve Downs, "What Next for Hell on Wheels?", 1986 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Correspondence, 1978-1986 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Role of CPUSA in TWU Local 100 and 1199, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- "Trade Union Organization and Workers' Consciousness: The Case of N.Y. Subway Workers" (M. Swerdlow), 1984 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Technological Change, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- "Politics of Productions", 1982-1986 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- "'The Last Trip is the Monkeymaker': Signs and Perceptions of Time and Space in the Occupational Folklore of N.Y. Subway Workers", 1987 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Race Relations in an Industrial Workplace, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Accommodations Papera, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Hell on Wheels -- New Directions, 1986-1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- TWU Contract, 1990-1992 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- TWU Local Election, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Hell on Wheels -- New Directions, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- TWU Contract, 1993-1995 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- New Directions/TWU, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- New Directions -- 1997 Election (Box 5, Folder 8)
- New Directions, 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- TWU Contract, 1999-1999 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- New Directions, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- TWU Contact, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- TWU -- General, 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- TWU -- General, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- TWU -- Media, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- TWU -- General, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- TWU -- General, 2004-2005 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- TWU -- General, 2005-2006 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- TWU -- Newspapers, 2005-2006 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- TWU -- General, 2006-2008 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Welcome to TWU, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- New York City Transit Authority Rules and Regulations, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Notebooks, 1979-1986 (Box 6, Folder 7-9, Box 7, Folder 1-7)
- Calendars, 1982-1986 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)